Finding Aid for Michigan Garden Clubs records, 1931-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Garden Clubs records 1931-2009
Michigan Garden Clubs.
(in 8 boxes)
7.3 linear feet
07101 Bn 2
The Michigan Garden Clubs was formed in 1931 as an organization of separate Michigan gardening groups. The record group includes administrative and historical files, activities files, awards, correspondence, yearbooks, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records of the Michigan Garden Clubs, Inc. were received by the Bentley Historical Library in April, 2007 (Donor No. 9842 ).
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The idea for the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan (FGCM, now Michigan Garden Clubs, Inc.) was conceived at a meeting on June 30, 1931 at the Women's League Building in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Forty representatives of 15 existing garden clubs in Michigan were present at the meeting, where a nominating committee for the new organization was appointed and a secretary and temporary president chosen. The first formal meeting took place in October of 1931 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. The Federation's first president, Mrs. Joseph Dexter, who later became president of the National Council of State Garden Clubs in 1941, was instrumental in laying the groundwork for many of the projects the organization was to undertake. Due to her efforts and those of her successors, by 1941 the organization had grown from its original 15 clubs to 121 clubs, with a membership of between five and six thousand.
The first bulletin of the organization was published in December, 1931. This later became its official publication, "Thru the Garden Gate", which FCGM has only recently decided (2007) to discontinue.
During World War II many of the programs that had been started were put on hold for the duration of the war. Several garden clubs in Michigan disbanded, but new members joined and the Federation continued. The Victory Garden program became its primary project and many members volunteered at the Red Cross, Bond drives, and at various camps and hospitals. The Federation was incorporated in 1941 and became the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan, Inc.
Following the war, the Victory Gardens program continued as the Peace Gardens and other projects were begun. These included work on the Michigan section of the Blue Star Memorial Highway (completed in 1946), the "Help for Holland" and "Help for Finland and Lapland" programs in which quantities of tools, seeds, fertilizer, and insecticides were sent to the Norwegian countries, and the planting of 1,254 Freedom Gardens following the government's call for growing more vegetables in 1947.
Conservation has always been a primary concern for the organization. Its first Conservation Conference took place in 1934 in Lansing, Michigan after the State Department's declaration that if 100 women could be found who were interested in learning about conservation, it would come and give a comprehensive program. These conferences continued yearly and beginning in 1947 were held at the Higgins Lake Conference center. The first Conservation Training School for Teachers took place at Higgins Lake that year as well. In 1941 the Federation began the Loda Lake Sanctuary, the first wildlife sanctuary of the Forest Service in the Great Lakes Region, and several other initiatives followed. One of the biggest of these was the purchase by FGCM in 1980 of a large tract of land on Lake Huron known as Grass Bay. This purchase, and subsequent land grants, are managed by the Nature Conservancy and have helped to secure many miles of protected shoreline along the lake.
Education has also been one of the priorities of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan. The first Flower Show School was organized in 1945 to standardize the judging of flower shows in the state (it was then called the Judging School Committee). Many more of these schools emerged, particularly in the early 1950s, when the Federation's Garden Therapy program was at its beginning. The first Landscape Design School was instituted in 1958 and a Landscape Critics Council was formed in 1961. A Landscape Design School was founded in Holland, Michigan in the same year. Also in 1961, an organization was created to manage scholarship funds and support students of horticulture, environmental education, and related fields. This was known as the Federation of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan. It was incorporated in 1961 and merged with the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan, Inc. in 2004.
In 1976 the first two Schools of Gardening were taught by Mrs. Paul Dunn. Upon completion of four courses, graduates were awarded certificates as Horticultural Consultants. These were the first of the Gardening Study Courses that the organization has continued to the present. A Gardening Consultant's Council was formed in 1980.
Through youth activities, education, celebrations, and campaigns, Michigan Garden Clubs, Inc. has and continues to play a major role in raising awareness about environmental issues, sustaining conservation initiatives, and beautifying the state of Michigan. Some of their involvements that were not mentioned above include Arbor Day, Michigan Garden Week, the establishment of Public Gardens, Roadside Beautification, the Frederick Meijer Gardens, the Daffodil Project, the Loda Lake Nature Preserve, and the Jo Russell Memorial Wildflower Project.
The records of the Michigan Garden Clubs are a synthesis of the collections kept by individual members of the organization over time. The structure of the finding aid reflects this in that several topics such as Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Newsletters, appear in multiple series of the collection. The record group is divided into seven series: Administration; Activities; Landscape Design Critics Council; Gardening Consultants Council; Ruth Knott files; Awards, Loda Lake Nature Preserve, and Yearbooks.
Subjects:
Michigan Garden Clubs.; Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan.; Gardening--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Environmental protection--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Loda Lake Wildflower Sanctuary.
Contributors:
Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administration
  The Administration series contains a wealth of historical background material in the form of both official publications and typed and handwritten reports. An organization historian existed for every two-year administration, providing consistent records of the organization's activities and achievements. These include organization membership, awards, educational courses, flower shows, and anniversaries. The series contains a nearly complete collection of Annual Meeting programs from 1934-2000, as well as documents relating to the Incorporation of the Foundation of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan in 1961 and its merger with the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan, Inc. in 2004. Resolutions, Annual Reports (including financial), Meeting Minutes, and records of National Conventions are more sparse, but may also be found in significant runs for some years.
  - Historian's Files
    - Chronology (Box 1)
    - Additional Involvements and Accomplishments (Box 1)
    - Reports of the Historian 1931-2001, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - List of Clubs 1931-1992 (Box 1)
      (includes gaps)
    - Resolutions 1964-1974 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of Presidents 1931-1971 (Box 1)
    - Life Membership Records 1961-1979 (Box 1)
    - Headquarters Building Records through 1976 (Box 1)
    - State and National Garden Club Scrapbook 1962-1965 (Box 1)
    - Documents Relating to the Incorporation and Dissolution of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Historical Files 1964-1997 (Box 1)
  - Meetings and Reports
    - Programs for State and Regional Annual Meetings 1934-2008 (Box 1)
      (includes some gaps, mostly complete)
    - Annual Reports of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan, Inc. 1955-1967 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting Minutes 1986, 1999, 2002, 2003, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes 1997-2007 (includes gaps; meeting minutes through 2005 can be found in the Ruth Knott files) (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports 1966, 1990, 1995, 1999-2004 (Box 1)
    - Reports of the Database Manager 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Meeting 2001 (Box 1)
    - Summaries of FCGM, Inc. Administrations 1993-2001 (Box 1)
    - Annual District Reports 1999, 2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (includes First Vice President Sharon Yantis' annual report for 1999)
  - National Conventions
    - National Convention Directives 1971 (Box 1)
    - National Convention Newsletters 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - National Convention 1978 (Box 1)
    - National Convention 1985 (Box 1)
    - National Convention Banners 1996 (Box 1)
    - National Convention 2005 (Box 1)
  - Regional Files
    - Summaries of Regional Garden Club Administrations 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports of State Presidents 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Central Region: Miscellaneous Newsletters, Reports, Planning sheets 2002-2008 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - State Board Directories 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Handbooks 1976, 1999, undated labeled "Property of First Vice President" (Box 1)
    - Compiled pamphlets
      - Program and Lecture Bulletin 1937 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Properties and Places of Interest 1939 (Box 1)
      - 1929-1949; The First Twenty Years: History of National of State Garden Clubs, Inc. (Box 1)
      - Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan 1931-1981 (Box 1)
    - Plaque on the 50th Anniversary of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Administrative How-Tos (Box 1)
      (starting a garden club, holding meetings, etc.)
    - Correspondence to Betty Colby, Historian 2001-2003 (Box 1)
      (much of what was contained in this correspondence has been integrated with the meeting minutes and reports above)
    - Event invitations and correspondence (Box 1)
    - Photograph of Governor Milliken and Miss Genevieve Gillette (Box 1)
    - Yearbooks 1932-1941 (bound) (Box 1)
    - Blue Star Memorial Program 2007 (Box 1)
    - District III Miscellaneous Files 2003 (Box 8)
    - District IV Miscellaneous Files 1992-2008 (Box 8)
    - Handbook (Box 8)
    - Local Club Information Forms 2005-2006 (Box 8)
    - Local Newsletters 2007-2008 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Local Files 1991-2009, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous National Garden Clubs Files 1992-2008 (Box 8)
    - Publicity Files 1991-1992 (Box 8)
    - State Secretary's File 1990s, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Activities
  The Michigan Garden Clubs were involved in numerous educational initiatives, Legislative Acts and other projects, records of which are kept in the Activities series. There is a large amount of material relating to Conservation efforts of the organization such as Waste Awareness in the late 1980s and early 1990s, and Conservation Conferences from the mid-1950s through the 1970s. Michigan's garden clubs were quite active in education as well. Several folders contain records of the numerous study courses it has offered, including documents, correspondence, and news clippings relating to the foundation of the Landscape Design School in Holland Michigan by Elsie Cook, one of the members of the club, in 1961.
  - Education
    - Basic Flower Arranging (Box 2)
    - Environmental Studies School (Box 2)
    - Gardening Study Courses 1975-2004 (Box 2)
    - Higgins Lake Environmental School (Box 2)
    - Landscape Design Study Courses (Box 2)
    - History of Landscape Design School, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Description of Study Programs (Box 2)
      - Requirements and Procedures to Become an Instructor (Box 2)
  - Projects
    - News clippings relating to Arbor Day and Liberty Tree (Box 2)
    - Blue Star Memorial, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Conservation Conferences 1955, 1959-1978, 1989, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Conservation Conferences Miscellaneous Materials
      - List of Conservation Resources (Box 2)
      - Guidelines for Pate Awards (Box 2)
    - Contests (Box 2)
    - The Daffodil Project (Box 2)
    - Garden Therapy (Box 2)
    - Grass Bay Project (Box 2)
    - Frederick Meijers Garden (Box 2)
    - Legislation connected with Garden Club initiatives (Box 2)
    - Loda Lake (Box 2)
    - Michigan Week (Box 2)
    - National Garden and U.S. Botanical Gardens Projects (Box 2)
    - Traverse Area, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Waste Awareness
      - Project file for 1987, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - Project file for 1988, 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Wildflower Project (Box 2)
    - World Gardening Project (Box 2)
- Landscape Design Critics Council
  There are two subseries in the Landscape Design Critics Council series: the first includes records of the presidents of the organization from 1965 to 2003; the second is made of up files kept by organization historians from 1962-1981. These are largely composed of meeting minutes, newsletters, and correspondence relating to the organization, but also include photographs, materials on Landscape Design Study Courses, and financial reports. There is some overlap between the two sections.
  - President Files
    - Mary Gerathy 1965 (Box 2)
    - Phyllis Evans 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Lenore Sampson 1967-1969 (Box 2)
    - Carrie Benjamin 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Lois Hartz 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - Helen Ross 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - Vera Sullivan 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - Pat Huxtable 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Lenore Sampson 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Marilyn Bar 1981-1983 (Box 3)
    - Florence Froelich 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - Dorothea Thomas 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - Elaine Gunderson 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Donna Schumann 1989-1991 (Box 3)
    - Jo Russell 1991-1993 (Box 3)
    - Ann Spaeth 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - Jane Raley 1995-1997 (Box 3)
    - Elizabeth Kuhlman 1997-1999 (Box 3)
    - Mary Pulick 1999-2001 (Box 3)
    - Charlotte Dashner 2001-2003 (Box 3)
    - Florence Smith 2005-2007 (Box 3)
  - Historical Files
    - Historical Files 1962-1981, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Landscape Design Critics Council Manual 1990 (Box 3)
    - Adventures in Landscaping by Betty Frankel (Box 3)
- Gardening Consultants Council
  The Gardening Consultants Council is a small series but contains similar types of materials: meeting minutes, correspondence, newsletters, and reports. It has materials relating to the Miriam Petrides Award and detailed organizational rosters and meeting attendance records.
  - Historian's File
    - Organization Officers (Box 3)
    - Bylaws (Box 3)
    - Reports, Agendas 1986-1995 (Box 3)
    - Annual Meeting Minutes 1981-1996 (Box 3)
  - Miriam Petrides Gardening Award (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 1981-2004 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1984-1990 (Box 3)
  - Membership Rosters 1981-1997 (Box 3)
  - Gardening Consultant's Council Symposium 2004 (Box 3)
    (includes photographs)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Scrapbook items (Box 3)
    - Certificate (Box 3)
    - Attendance Records (Box 3)
- Ruth Knott Files
  The Ruth Knott Files make up one entire series of the collection. Ruth Knott was the Director of Michigan's District IV garden clubs, located in western Michigan, from 2003-2005. A large portion of the collection is made up of newsletters, meeting minutes, and correspondence kept by her during her administration. Historical/background materials on some of the garden clubs in District IV and newsletters from those and other districts within Michigan are also represented.
  - Garden Club Historical/Background Information
    - Canadian Lakes Garden Club (Box 3)
    - Muskegon County Garden Club (Box 3)
    - All Seasons Garden Club (Box 3)
    - Kent Garden Club (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - District I-VI Newsletters 2003-2005, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Four Seasons Garden Club 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Holland Horticultural Club April 2002 (Box 3)
    - National Garden Clubs, Inc. August 2003-July 2005 (Box 4)
    - Kent Garden Club July 2003-May 2005 (Box 4)
    - Lowell Showboat Garden Club August 2002 (Box 4)
    - Mason County June 26-27, 2004 (Box 4)
      (notice of flower show only)
    - Muskegon County Garden Club 2003-2004 (Box 4)
  - Meetings
    - District IV Meetings 1987-2004, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes 2001-2004 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondence 2001-2005 (Box 4)
      (includes six photographs)
    - Guidelines for District Meetings (Box 4)
    - Information on Thru The Garden Gate Submissions (Box 4)
    - Life Membership Information (Box 4)
    - News clippings 1981, 1982, 2004 (Box 4)
      (includes eight unlabelled photographs)
    - Program Ideas for Clubs (Box 4)
    - Reports of Garden Club Presidents 2005 (Box 4)
- Awards
  The fifth series is composed National and State Awards received by organizations, districts, and individuals in Michigan. Because awards are given for projects, each "award" is a scrapbook describing a particular event or project. This series, therefore, is a good resource for exploring the activities of different groups within the Michigan Garden Clubs. The awards were given between 1970 and 2003. Supplemental files at the end of the series include news clippings and correspondence relating to the awards, additional certificates, and compiled lists and information about awards winners.
  - Chronological
    - Award #40, The Owens Trophy 1970 (Box 4)
    - Award #26, The Spillers Medal for Landscape Design 1973 (Box 4)
    - Award #41, The Hazel Johnson Silver Trophy for Conservation Education 1978 (Box 4)
    - Award #6-5, The Lucile Droege Mauntel Certificate for Conservation 1978 (Box 4)
    - Award #6-5, The Lucile Droege Mauntel Certificate for Conservation 1980 (Box 4)
    - Award #41, The Hazel Johnson Silver Trophy for Conservation Education 1980 (Box 4)
    - Award #44, Environmental Action Leadership Medal 1982 (Box 4)
    - Award #30, Green Rosette for District Flower Show, District II-B Michigan 1982 (Box 4)
    - National Council Land Trust Award 1982 (Box 4)
    - Award #44, Environmental Action Leadership Medal 1984 (Box 4)
    - National Council Land Trust Award 1984 (Box 4)
    - National Council Land Trust Award 1985 (Box 4)
    - Award #40, The Hubert Bond Owens Silver Trophy for Landscape Critics 1989 (Box 4)
    - Environmental Awareness 1992 (Box 4)
      (53rd Annual Conservation Conference)
    - Horticulture B, Certificate of Appreciation, District II-B 1943 (Box 4)
    - Flower Show Red Rosette #15 1998 (Box 4)
    - Standard Flower Show Red Rosette #30 2003 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Awards Brochures 1973, 1992, 1995, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Certificates
      - General 1973-2002 (Box 4)
      - District II-B 1991-2005 (Box 4)
        (includes five photographs)
    - Correspondence and News clippings 1965-2001 (Box 4)
    - Photograph of Award Recipients and Board Members April 5, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Scale of Points for Judging National Council Yearbook Award #16B (Box 4)
    - District Awards 2006 (Box 4)
- Loda Lake Nature Preserve
  The Loda Lake Nature Preserve series consists of materials related to the Loda Lake Nature Preserve in Newaygo, Michigan. The Michigan Garden Clubs founded Loda Lake in the 1930s and continue to maintain the site in the present day. The bulk of the series consists of correspondence, publicity, and programming materials.
  - Birds 1953 (Box 5)
  - Boardwalk 1984-1985 (Box 5)
  - Botanical Description (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1937-1971, 1980-2005, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence Re: Loda Lake History 1976-1979 (Box 5)
  - Chairperson Job Description (Box 5)
  - Financial Information 1994-2004 (Box 5)
  - Historical Materials relating to the founding of Loda Lake 1914-1990 (Box 5)
  - Garden Gate Articles, 1977-2001 (Box 5)
  - Guides and Maps 1970s-1990s (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - Plant Lists 1950s (Box 5)
  - Plantings 1982 (Box 5)
  - Photos and Negatives 1997 (Box 5)
  - Publicity 1970s-2008 (Box 5)
  - Reports to Board 1975-2005 (Box 5)
  - Sign (Box 5)
  - Slide Program (Box 5)
  - Trail Finance, Planning, and Production 1996 (Box 5)
  - Trail History 1978-1985 (Box 5)
  - Visiting Gardens 1980-1999 (Box 5)
  - Mrs. Grace Votey History (Box 5)
  - Wildflowers 1947-2005 (Box 5)
- Yearbooks 1997-2009
  The final series, Yearbooks, consists of local chapter yearbooks from 1997 to 2009. The bulk of the yearbooks are from the period 2007-2009.
  - 1997-2008, 14 folders (Box 6)
  - 2008-2009, 5 folders (Box 7)
Related Material
Issues of the organization newsletter Thru the Garden Gate, have been removed and separately cataloged.